Let’s say you’re trying to
find some solid information
about a serious health
problem that concerns you,
like high blood pressure,
or diabetes.
Yet, everywhere you look,
someone’s trying to sell you
something like vitamins,
yoga mats, blenders, drugs.
Well, breathe a
sigh of relief
because all we bring
you are the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that there
has been a steep rise
in cases of asthma
over the years
and that much of that
can be attributed
to an increase in
air pollution?
Well, it turns out that some diets
can improve our respiratory defense
against lung disease
and infection.
Here’s our first story.
Outdoor air pollution may be the 9th
leading cause of death and disability
in the world, responsible for millions
of deaths from lung cancer,
emphysema, heart disease,
stroke, and respiratory infection.
In the U.S., living in a polluted
city was associated
with a 16, 27, and 28% increase in total,
cardiovascular, and lung cancer death,
compared to living in
a city with cleaner air.
Living in a city with polluted air
may lead to up to a 75% increase
in the risk of a heart attack.
No one wants to be living in a traffic jam,
but it's better than dying in a traffic jam.
In addition to causing deaths,
air pollution is also the cause of
a number of health problems.
It may not only
exacerbate asthma,
but also increase the risk of
developing asthma in the first place.
These pollutants may
trigger liver disease,
even increase the
risk of diabetes.
Even when atmospheric pollutants
are within legally established limits,
they can be harmful to health.
So what can we do about it?
Paper after paper describing all the
terrible things air pollution can do to us,
but most failed to
mention public policy.
We're making great strides in
demonstrating the harmful effects,
but public authorities are not using
these data to reduce emissions,
as they might
inconvenience the population
and therefore might not be
politically acceptable.
To treat the cause, we need
better vehicle inspections,
efficient public transport,
bus lanes, bicycle lanes,
even urban tolls to
help clean up the air.
While we're waiting for all that,
is there anything we can
do to protect ourselves?
Well, our body naturally
has detoxifying enzymes,
not only in our liver
but lining our airways.
Studies showing that people born
with less effective detox enzymes
have an exaggerated allergic
response to diesel exhaust,
suggesting that these enzymes
actively combat the inflammation
caused by pollutants in the air.
A significant part of the population has
these substandard forms of the enzyme,
but either way, what can
we do to boost the activity
of whichever detoxification
enzymes we do have?
Well, if you remember, broccoli
can dramatically boost the activity
of the detox enzymes in our liver,
but what about our lungs?
Researchers fed some smokers a large
stalk of broccoli every day for 10 days
to see if it would affect the level
of inflammation within their bodies.
Why smokers?
Because smoking
is so inflammatory
that you can end up
with elevated C-reactive protein levels
for up to 30 years after quitting,
and that inflammation can start almost
immediately after we start smoking,
so it's critical to never
start in the first place.
But if you do, you can cut your level
of that inflammation biomarker, CRP,
nearly in half, after just 10 days
eating a lot of broccoli.
Appears to cut inflammation
in nonsmokers as well,
maybe explaining in part why eating
more than two cups of broccoli,
cabbage, cauliflower, kale, or
other cruciferous veggies a day
is associated with 20%
reduced risk of dying,
compared to eating a third
of a cup a day or less.
So what about air pollution?
We know the cruciferous compound
is the most potent known inducer
of our detox enzymes.
And so most of the research has
been its ability to fight cancer,
but here for the first time, they
tried to see if it could combat
the pro-inflammatory impact of
pollutants such as diesel exhaust.
They put some human lung
lining cells in a Petri dish
and this is how many detox
enzymes are produced.
Drip on some broccoli goodness
and you get this many.
Yeah, but we don't inhale broccoli,
we don't snort it; we eat it.
Can it still get into
our lungs and help?
Yes, two days of broccoli
sprout consumption,
then you suck some
cells out of their nose,
and up to 100 times more
detox enzyme expression
compared to eating a non-cruciferous
vegetable, alfalfa sprouts.
Now, all we have to do is squirt
some diesel exhaust up their nose,
which is what some
UCLA researchers did,
an amount equal to daily rush hour
exposure on a Los Angeles freeway.
Within six hours, the number of
inflammatory cells in their nose
shot up and continued to rise.
But in the group that had been
getting a broccoli sprout extract,
the inflammation went
down and stayed down.
Since the dose in these
studies is equivalent
to the consumption of
1 or 2 cups of broccoli,
their study demonstrates
the potential preventive
and therapeutic
potential of broccoli.
But if broccoli is so powerful at
suppressing this inflammatory
immune response, might it interfere
with normal immune function?
After all the battle with viruses like
influenza can happen in the nose.
Let's drip some flu viruses
into the nostrils of broccoli
sprout eaters and find out.
And what you get is
the best of both worlds:
less inflammation, yet an
improved immune response.
After eating a package of
broccoli sprouts every day,
our body is able to keep
the virus in check,
potentially offering a safe,
low-cost strategy
for reducing influenza risk
among high risk populations.
So better immune function,
yet less inflammation,
potentially reducing the impact
of pollution on allergic disease
and asthma—at least for an
enthusiastic broccoli consumer.
But what about cancer,
detoxifying air pollutants
throughout the rest of our body?
We didn't know until now.
Off to China where they have some
of the worst air pollution in the world.
And by day one, those
getting the broccoli sprouts
were able to get rid of 60%
more benzene from their bodies,
a rapid, highly durable elevation
in the detoxification
of a known human carcinogen.
Now this was using broccoli sprouts,
which are highly concentrated,
equivalent to about 5 cups
of broccoli a day.
So we don't know how well
more modest doses would work,
but if they do, eating broccoli
could provide a frugal means
to attenuate the long-term
health risks of air pollution.
Finally today,
if the nitrites in foods like ham
and bacon cause lung damage,
what about processed meat
with “no nitrites added”?
Recently, the World Health Organization
classified processed meat,
also known as cured meat—bacon, ham,
hot dogs, lunch meat, and sausage—
as definitively cancer-
causing in humans.
As if that’s not enough, high
processed meat consumption
has also been associated with
increased risk of dying prematurely
from all causes put together
and is a risk factor
for several major chronic diseases,
such as type 2 diabetes,
coronary heart disease, and stroke.
But what about lung issues like asthma?
Nitrites are added to processed
meats as preservatives
to preserve their pink
(so they don’t turn gray),
keeping them less rancid
tasting, and to prevent
the growth of diseases like botulism.
But put that same sodium
nitrite in the drinking water
of lab animals and
they develop emphysema.
They nearly all developed emphysema.
But that’s all the scientific
knowledge we had on the subject
coming into 2007, until this
study, which found that
frequent cured meat consumption
is associated with increased risk
for developing diseases like
emphysema in people, too–
chronic obstructive
pulmonary disease (COPD).
Eating it like every other
day appeared to triple the odds
of severe COPD.
But it was just a snapshot-in-time
study; so, we don’t know
which came first, the
sausage or the COPD.
For that, we need prospective studies
that follow people over time,
and the big twin Harvard
studies in both women and men
both found that the risk
of newly diagnosed COPD
increased with a greater
consumption of cured meats.
Currently, we now have studies involving
hundreds of thousands of people,
showing that higher intakes of
processed meat were associated with
a 40% increased risk of COPD.
It comes out to like an 8% higher risk
of COPD for each hot
dog you eat all week
or each weekly breakfast link
sausage. What is going on?
Yes, there are advanced glycation
end-products, so-called glycotoxins,
that may be proinflammatory;
there’s the saturated fat
that can also trigger
inﬂammation in the airways;
the high salt content can present a
potential risk for lung inflammation;
or the increase in systemic
inflammation in general.
But the reason attention
has focused on the nitrites
is because nitrites may actually
be one of the mechanisms
by which tobacco smoke causes
diseases like emphysema.
Yes, cured meats are the principal
source of dietary nitrites,
but nitrites are also
byproducts of tobacco smoke.
One of the main constituents, besides
the carbon monoxide and nicotine,
are nitrogen oxides that are
converted in the lung to nitrites.
The way nitrites appear to
cause lung damage is by affecting
connective tissue proteins
like collagen and elastin.
That’s what helps keep the
airspaces in your lungs open,
but nitrite can modify these
proteins in a way that mimic
age-related damage, including
the fragmentation of elastin.
With that much lung injury,
it’s logical to assume
processed meat consumption could
also exacerbate the disease
of those who already have it.
And indeed, cured meat consumption
increases risk of COPD patients
ending up back in the hospital, about
twice the risk for those eating
more than average, and it appears
the more you eat, the worse it is.
Regarding lung health, processed meat
intake has been associated with
a likely increased risk of lung cancer,
a decline in lung function,
and chronic obstructive
pulmonary diseases.
But, what about asthma?
High processed meat consumption
has been associated with
higher asthma symptoms as well.
We knew about the higher maternal
intake of meat before pregnancy,
potentially increasing the risk of
wheezing in her children later on
(based on a study of more than
a thousand mother-child pairs).
And we’re not talking about
aspirating meat into your lungs
and being misdiagnosed with asthma.
Those who ate the most cured meats
were 76% more likely
to experience worsening asthma
than those who ate the least.
Since obesity is a likely
risk factor for asthma, though,
maybe the influence of the
meat is just indirect,
by contributing to weight gain?
That might be a small part of it,
but the main effect appears to be direct,
suggesting a deleterious role of
cured meat independent of weight.
Put all those studies together and
processed meat intake appears to be
an important target for the prevention
of adult asthma in the first place.
Even if you don’t have any lung
issues, processed meat consumption
was negatively associated with
measures of normal lung function,
while fruit and vegetable consumption
and dietary total antioxidant
capacity was associated
with better lung function.
But wait, you say. I just eat
all natural, uncured hot dogs,
with NO NITRATES OR NITRITES
ADDED, in all caps.
But if you magnifying glass
the small print, it says
“except those naturally occurring in…
cultured celery juice.”
See, to avoid saying they added
nitrites, what they do is
add something that has a lot of
nitrates, like celery and a bacteria
that converts the nitrates to nitrites.
So, they are adding nitrites.
They’re just straight-up duping consumers.
We didn’t add any nitrites
except, of course…
for all the nitrites we added.
We care about your health;
so, no nitrites added.
Who wants pepperoni with nitrites?
So, we just added lots of nitrites.
We would never add any nitrites.
Now, just let the piggy picture
distract you from the fact
that we just lied to your face.
Hormel was my favorite.
“Except for those naturally occurring
in seasoning”—pretty slick.
Europe doesn’t allow this
kind of consumer fraud,
demanding manufacturers explicitly
label it as containing nitrites.
You can’t even call it natural.
When Consumer Reports put it to the
test, they found the nitrite levels
in all the products were
essentially the same;
so “no nitrites” doesn’t mean no nitrites.
Consumer Reports and the Center
for Science in the Public Interest
have petitioned to stop
this misleading practice.
Nitrites are nitrites.
“Their chemical composition
is absolutely the same,
and so are the health eﬀects.”
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books were
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of “How Not to Age”.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.